Big Joe Turner Papers (Ahmet Ertegun Collection) ARC.0105
Library and Archives
Big Joe Turner Papers (Ahmet Ertegun Collection)
Bulk, 1976-1986
1945-1986
ARC.0105
Library and Archives
2.42 Linear feet (1 records carton, 1 shared oversize box)
The Big Joe Turner Papers (Ahmet Ertegun Collection) highlight the latter part of Turner's 60-year career as a pioneering and influential blues singer. The collection dates from 1945 to 1986, with the bulk of the material focusing on the period from 1976 to 1986. Materials include awards and certificates, business files, correspondence, memorials, personal files, photographic material, and publications. Of note are Turner's 1984 and 1985 Grammy Award nomination cards, information regarding the events and documentation surrounding Turners' search for his birth certificate, and correspondence from notable figures, including Dick Clark, Ahmet Ertegun, Doc Pomus, and Jann Wenner. The collection also includes information relating to the benefit concert Turner's wife, Pat, and his friends were organizing to help pay for the artist's skyrocketing medical bills. Turner passed away two weeks before the scheduled show in 1985. The collection contains two guest books from his funeral, as well as letters of condolence to Pat acknowledging her husband's significant contributions to the music world and the history of rock and roll. The materials in the collection are organized by type and then alphabetically by file title.
Biographical Note
1911 May 18 Born Joseph Vernon Turner, Jr. in Kansas City, Mo.
1938 December 23 Appears at "Spirituals to Swing" concert at Carnegie Hall in New York City.
1939 Releases first single, "Roll 'em Pete," with boogie woogie pianist Pete Johnson. With Albert Ammons and Meade Lux Lewis, begins a five-year residency at New York's Cafe Society.
1946 August 3 "My Gal's a Jockey" becomes Turner's first single to make the Billboard R&B chart.
1954 May 8 "Shake, Rattle and Roll" enters the Billboard charts, peaks at #1 on the R&B charts, and #2 on the Pop charts.
1956 Appears in the film, Shake, Rattle and Roll.
1983 Album, Blues Train, is released. Inducted into the Blues Hall of Fame.
1985 November 24 Dies in Inglewood, Ca.
1987 January 21 Posthumously inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame.
Big Joe Turner was among the first to mix R&B with boogie-woogie, resulting in jump blues, a style that presaged the birth of rock and roll. Turner’s original recording of “Shake, Rattle and Roll,” cut for Atlantic Records in 1954, remains one of the cornerstones of the rock and roll revolution. Turner’s lengthy career touched on most developments in popular music, taking him from the big bands of the Swing Era to boogie-woogie, rhythm and blues, and rock and roll. Turner recorded prolifically in the 1940s for various labels, including Decca, National, and Aladdin. He worked with Pete Johnson, as well as a number of other pianists, including such giants as Albert Ammons, Willie “the Lion” Smith, and Meade Lux Lewis. In 1946, Turner had his first R&B hit, “My Gal’s a Jockey,” released on Herb Abramson’s National label. Abramson would go on to cofound Atlantic Records with Ahmet Ertegun in 1948. In 1951, Ertegun brought Turner to Atlantic Records, where he cut a string of rhythm and blues and early rock and roll classics over the next decade; among them were “Chains of Love,” “Sweet Sixteen,” “Honey Hush,” Shake, Rattle and Roll,” “Flip Flop and Fly,” and “Corrine Corinna.” Pianist Fats Domino accompanied Turner on the romping “TV Mama.” “Shake, Rattle and Roll” and “Honey Hush” topped the R&B charts for three and eight weeks, respectively.
In the 1960s, after the first wave of rock and roll had died down, Turner returned to blues and boogie-woogie. He moved to Los Angeles, where he recorded with jazz legends like Dizzy Gillespie, Count Basie, and Roy Eldridge for some well-received albums on the Pablo label. The 1983 album Blues Train, on which he was backed by Roomful of Blues and produced by Doc Pomus, was a late-career success. Having outlasted trends until his sound had became timeless, Big Joe Turner continued to record and perform until his death in 1985.
Sources
"Big Joe Turner Biography." Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum. Accessed May 26, 2011. http://rockhall.com/inductees/big-joe-turner/bio/.
Access Restrictions
Collection is CLOSED.
Custodial History note
The Big Joe Turner Papers (Ahmet Ertegun Collection) were received by The Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, Inc. as a gift from Ertegun in 1994.
Separated Materials
Periodicals have been transferred to the library collection. Please search for the "Big Joe Turner Papers" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles. If you are unable to find what you are looking for, consult the Library and Archives staff to ensure these materials are available.
Related Materials
These materials constitute a part of the Ahmet Ertegun Collection.
Atlantic Recording Corporation; Turner, Joe, 1911-1985; Awards; Blues (Music); Blues-rock music; Boogie woogie (Music); Business records; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence; Doo-wop (Music); Guitar music (Rock); Legal instruments; Memorials; Musicians--United States--Biography; Negatives (photographic); Pamphlets; Photographs; Popular music--United States; Printed ephemera; Rhythm and blues music; Singers--United States--Biography; Transparencies
- Awards and certificates
  - Awards and certificates, 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Grammy awards nomination and information, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Business files
  - Business papers, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - California Afro-American Museum artifact control sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flyers, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed lyrics, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence
  - Letters, 1942-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Telegrams, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Memorials
  - Big Joe Turner memorial service, "Friends Who Called" book from Angelus Funeral Home, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memorial and benefit concerts, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Personal files
  - Biographical information, 1976-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Passport information, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Work permit, 1974 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photographic material
  - Negatives and transparencies, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Black and white publicity photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Publications
  - Clippings
    - 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pamphlets, 1974, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Oversize materials, 1977-1985, undated (Box-folder OS1-6)
  General note
  This file contains oversize awards and certificates, clippings, and a drawing of Turner, "King of the Blues," by Sean McNair.